JOE: If someone has an autistic
child or children, they can find
that their extended family and
friends, can become key parts of
their informal support network.
This is made easier when family and
friends become aware of a child’s
autism diagnosis at an early stage,
and makes it easier for them to
understand any issues, what it
means and how it affects the family.
BETH: Parents of children with
autism should first relay basic
information to their potential
informal support network about autism
and how it affects their child.
Extended family and friends will
probably respond in different ways to a
child’s autism diagnosis and behaviour.
Some might be ready to offer
support straight away, however
others might take a bit longer
to understand how they can help.
Some family and friends might find
it hard to give support or they might
respond in ways that aren’t very helpful.
JOE: It is important that people
acknowledge the feelings of
family and friends as they might
be having trouble understanding
the diagnosis and what it means.
It’s important for anyone relying
on family and friends to make them
aware of how autism affects their
child’s behaviour, for example, the
child may sometimes get overwhelmed
and needs quiet time on their own.
BETH: Someone offering informal support
needs to be told how best to connect
with the child, their likes and dislikes,
and the best ways to communicate.
Extended family get-togethers and
activities that suit the child’s
needs and abilities, could be
organised to facilitate this.
JOE: Unhelpful reactions usually happen
because people aren’t sure how to respond,
don’t understand or feel uncomfortable.
Telling close friends and family about
a child's autism diagnosis can help them
understand what this means and opening
up about what help and support the
whole family needs can be beneficial.
BETH: They may be able to help with
everyday things, so parents have more time
to focus on themselves or their child or
offer emotional support in times of need.
Other groups that can help are
national charities, and it may help
by listening to or reading other
people's experiences of autism online
and joining local support groups.
JOE: There are many people with experience
of autism either directly or indirectly
offering support and sharing their
stories on forums and social media.
People don’t have to have to talk to
others in online groups, but it can be
helpful to look at what they're saying.
BETH: Comments on social media and
forums are often based on personal
experience and should not be taken purely
as advice, but could be more help as a
source of experience based knowledge.
National charities such as National
Autistic Society have Facebook, Twitter
and online communities can also be
looked at as possible areas of support.